<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: XAMPP | Will Anderson]]></title>
  <link href="http://willi.am/blog/categories/xampp/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://willi.am/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-29T13:23:27-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://willi.am/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Will Anderson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creating XAMPP Alias Directories]]></title>
    <link href="http://willi.am/blog/2011/02/24/creating-xampp-alias-directories/"/>
    <updated>2011-02-24T12:35:42-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://willi.am/blog/2011/02/24/creating-xampp-alias-directories</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you&rsquo;ve read my post on <a href="/blog/2009/01/14/wamp-alias-directories/">adding aliases to WampServer</a>,
you may be curious about how to add aliases to XAMPP.
While WampServer has a nice (if somewhat buggy) tool for adding Apache aliases, XAMPP does not.
Fortunately, creating XAMPP alias directories by hand is pretty easy.</p>

<h2>Preparing to Create XAMPP Alias Directories</h2>

<p>The first thing you&rsquo;ll want to do is add an alias directory to your XAMPP install.
If you&rsquo;re running Windows, create the following folder.</p>

<p><code>
C:\xampp\apache\conf\alias
</code></p>

<p>Next, you&rsquo;ll need to change your Apache configuration file.
You can find it under <code>C:\xampp\apache\conf\httpd.conf</code>.
To make changes, you&rsquo;ll need to edit it as an administrator.
If you&rsquo;re running Windows Vista or above, your best bet is to open Notepad as an administrator and then open httpd.conf.
To open Notepad (or any other application) as an administrator, right-click on it and select &ldquo;Run as administrator&rdquo;.
You can also launch Notepad as an administrator from the start menu with <code>Ctrl+Shift+Enter</code> while Notepad is selected.</p>

<p>Once you&rsquo;ve opened httpd.conf, add the following to the end and save it.</p>

<p><code>
Include "conf/alias/*"
</code></p>

<p>Now Apache will look in the alias folder for more configuration files.
This way you can add an alias by simply adding a new configuration file to the conf/alias/ folder.</p>

<h2>Creating XAMPP Alias Directories</h2>

<p>Let&rsquo;s add some XAMPP alias directories.
Suppose you want to add an alias called &ldquo;dev&rdquo;.
First, download <a href="/uploads/xampp-alias-template.txt">this alias template file</a> and place it in the alias folder.
Rename it to &ldquo;dev.conf&rdquo; (or whatever you called your alias).
You&rsquo;ll need to edit the template (again, as an administrator) and replace &ldquo;DIRECTORY&rdquo; (it&rsquo;s there twice) with the path to the alias and &ldquo;ALIAS&rdquo; with the name of your alias.
In our example, it looks something like this:</p>

<p>```
<directory "c:\users\foo\programming\dev"></p>

<pre><code>#
# Possible values for the Options directive are "None", "All",
# or any combination of:
#   Indexes Includes FollowSymLinks SymLinksifOwnerMatch ExecCGI MultiViews
#
# Note that "MultiViews" must be named *explicitly* --- "Options All"
# doesn't give it to you.
#
# The Options directive is both complicated and important.  Please see
# http://httpd.apache.org/docs/2.2/mod/core.html#options
# for more information.
#
Options Indexes FollowSymLinks Includes ExecCGI

#
# AllowOverride controls what directives may be placed in .htaccess files.
# It can be "All", "None", or any combination of the keywords:
#   Options FileInfo AuthConfig Limit
#
AllowOverride All

#
# Controls who can get stuff from this server.
#     Order allow,deny
Allow from all
</code></pre>

<p></Directory></p>

<p>Alias /dev &ldquo;C:\users\foo\programming\dev&rdquo;
```</p>

<p>Restart Apache (you can do so from the XAMPP control panel) and check out <a href="http://localhost/dev.">http://localhost/dev.</a>
You can repeat this process with other aliases to add more XAMPP alias directories.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
