<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: SendGrid | Will Anderson]]></title>
  <link href="http://willi.am/blog/categories/sendgrid/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://willi.am/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-02T00:36:58-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://willi.am/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Will Anderson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Plugin WP SendGrid]]></title>
    <link href="http://willi.am/blog/2011/12/15/new-plugin-wp-sendgrid/"/>
    <updated>2011-12-15T08:49:43-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://willi.am/blog/2011/12/15/new-plugin-wp-sendgrid</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A couple of months ago, I had the opportunity to attend an <a href="http://www.apihackday.com/">API Hackday</a> event in Bloomington.
At the event, I created some cool WordPress tools using <a href="http://www.twilio.com/">Twilio</a>, but I ended up having some free time
(because Twilio&rsquo;s API is so easy to use!), so I wrote another plugin called <a href="http://www.itsananderson.com/plugins/wp-sendgrid/">WP SendGrid</a> using the SendGrid API.</p>

<p>This plugin extends WordPress' <code>wp_mail()</code> function to use SendGrid&rsquo;s API for all emails.
This was useful to me because I&rsquo;ve never been able to figure out how to get PHP to send emails in Windows.
In the past, when I&rsquo;ve worked on projects that send emails, I always had to upload it to a Linux server to test the email functionality.
If anything didn&rsquo;t work, I had to edit locally, then upload again to test it.
After a few iterations, that gets really old.
With WP SendGrid, I can send emails from my local machine, so debugging issues is <strong>much</strong> easier.</p>

<p>Fast-forward a few months.
This week I decided to spend a little more time polishing the plugin.
I&rsquo;d only spent about 45 minutes on it at the HackDay, which shows how simple it is to use SendGrid&rsquo;s API.
What I put together was enough to meet my needs, but I was using hardcoded values, and wasn&rsquo;t considering every edge-case.
After a few more hours of work, I had a complete plugin with a nice configuration UI.</p>

<p>If you develop for WordPress on Windows, or you have trouble sending email from PHP on another platform, you&rsquo;ll want to check this plugin out.
<a href="http://www.itsananderson.com/plugins/wp-sendgrid/">Visit the plugin page</a>.</p>

<p>If you run into any issues, let me know by submitting a ticket on the <a href="https://github.com/codeawhile/wp-sendgrid">GitHub</a> project.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
