<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Review | Will Anderson]]></title>
  <link href="http://willi.am/blog/categories/review/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://willi.am/"/>
  <updated>2015-05-24T19:18:36-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://willi.am/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Will Anderson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Netgear Nighthawk AC1900 (R7000) Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://willi.am/blog/2015/02/04/netgear-nighthawk-ac1900-r7000-review/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-04T22:13:14-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://willi.am/blog/2015/02/04/netgear-nighthawk-ac1900-r7000-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I bought a new Wi-Fi router about a year ago, and I&rsquo;ve been so happy with it that I decided to write a review.</p>

<h2>The Goods</h2>

<p>Netgear has a truly impressive lineup of high-quality routers in their Nighthawk series.</p>

<p>When I purchased the Nighthawk R7000, it was the only Nighthawk available, but now there are three options.</p>

<h3>Nighthawk AC1900 (R7000)</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00F0DD0I6?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=213733&amp;creative=393185&amp;creativeASIN=B00F0DD0I6&amp;linkCode=shr&amp;tag=itsananderson-20&amp;linkId=BOLZOX4JTJAYBWR2"><img src="http://itsananderson.blob.core.windows.net/post-images/nighthawk-r7000.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>This is the router I purchased.
At $176, it is now the cheapest one in the series, but don&rsquo;t let that fool you.
It&rsquo;s a beast.</p>

<h3>Nighthawk X4 AC2350 (R7500)</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00MRVJY5C?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=213733&amp;creative=393177&amp;creativeASIN=B00MRVJY5C&amp;linkCode=shr&amp;tag=itsananderson-20&amp;linkId=VIPUHQZWDGEZTHRJ&amp;f_rd_m=ATVPDKIKX0DER&amp;pf_rd_s=center-2&amp;pf_rd_r=15AA64WNHBH3N7C3AG2S&amp;pf_rd_t=101&amp;pf_rd_p=2034761682&amp;pf_rd_i=9524228011"><img src="http://itsananderson.blob.core.windows.net/post-images/nighthawk-r7500.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>This model has an additional antena, a faster processor, and boasts improved range and faster bandwidth. It costs about $100 more than the R7000. This router uses a more advanced radio than the R7000 that apparently has higher throughput and reliability. That being said, I haven&rsquo;t experienced any problems with the throughput or reliability of the R7000.</p>

<h3>Nighthawk X6 AC3200 (R8000)</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00KWHMR6G?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=213733&amp;creative=393177&amp;creativeASIN=B00KWHMR6G&amp;linkCode=shr&amp;tag=itsananderson-20&amp;linkId=62Y4XCEYOOJRGP7I&amp;f_rd_m=ATVPDKIKX0DER&amp;pf_rd_s=center-2&amp;pf_rd_r=15AA64WNHBH3N7C3AG2S&amp;pf_rd_t=101&amp;pf_rd_p=2034761682&amp;pf_rd_i=9524228011"><img src="http://itsananderson.blob.core.windows.net/post-images/nighthawk-r8000.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>This model has 6 antenas, which again boosts range and bandwidth.
It also supports a third Wi-Fi band, and assigns slower and faster devices to different bands, boosting performance for fast devices.
This model is only about $5 more than the R7500 ($105 more than the R7000), so if I were to upgrade, this is the model I would choose, because of it&rsquo;s significantly improved bandwidth.</p>

<h2>Price</h2>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a side-by-side comparison of the different models.</p>

<table>
    <tr><th>Model</th><th>Price</th></tr>
    <tr><td>Nighthawk (R7000)</td><td>$176</td></tr>
    <tr><td>&nbsp;Nighthawk X4 (R7500)</td><td>$279</td></tr>
    <tr><td>&nbsp;Nighthawk X6 (R8000)</td><td>$283</td></tr>
</table>


<p>When I first considered this router, the price was what gave me the most pause.
In the past, the most I&rsquo;d paid for a router was about $40, so this seemed like a significant price bump.
In the end, the only reason I bought it was because a friend had bought one and was very happy with it.</p>

<p>After using it for a year, I don&rsquo;t think I&rsquo;ll ever buy a &ldquo;cheap&rdquo; router again.
In the case of Wi-Fi routers, it seems that &ldquo;you get what you pay for&rdquo; holds true.</p>

<h2>Reliability and Performance</h2>

<p>My primary reason for upgrading my router was that my previous router, an older Linksys in the $30-40 range, didn&rsquo;t reliably reach the entire house.
After enough complaints from one roommate who&rsquo;s bedroom was in the far corner of the house, I decided to upgrade.</p>

<p>After installing the R7000, I&rsquo;ve stopped having router issues.
The signal reaches to every corner of the house, and has never cut out.</p>

<p>I eventually even swapped out the Ethernet cables in my two desktop computers, replacing them with this <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B007GMPZ0A?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=213733&amp;creative=393185&amp;creativeASIN=B007GMPZ0A&amp;linkCode=shr&amp;tag=itsananderson-20&amp;linkId=E3Z7SM7WKO2M3UVP&amp;psc=1">Dual Band Wireless PCI Express adapter</a>.
Even after getting rid of the hard line, I get blazing fast speeds on both machines.</p>

<h2>Extra Features</h2>

<h3>Mounting Slots</h3>

<p>One of the things I took advantage of immediately was the slots on the back for mounting it on a wall.
Moving the router to a more central location in my downstairs hallway provided even better coverage throughout the house.</p>

<p><img src="http://itsananderson.blob.core.windows.net/post-images/mounted-router.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><small><em>(yes, that&rsquo;s a Raspberry Pi unceremoniously dangling from the router. Don&rsquo;t judge me)</em></small></p>

<p>Pro tip: make sure there&rsquo;s a power outlet within easy reach of your desired location <strong>before</strong> you start screwing in drywall anchors :)</p>

<h3>Web-based WPS Button</h3>

<p>Most routers support WPS. This allows new clients to connect to a network by clicking a physical button on the router.
This is convenient, but who wants to have to get up and walk over to the router.</p>

<p>Fortunately the Nighthawk web UI has a button you can push to do the same thing.</p>

<p><img src="http://itsananderson.blob.core.windows.net/post-images/soft-wps-button.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><img src="http://itsananderson.blob.core.windows.net/post-images/wifi-client-connected.png" alt="" /></p>

<h3>Easy Firmware Upgrade</h3>

<p>Most of my past routers have had a really archaic update process. Usually you have to manually flash the firmware and go through a convoluted restart process.</p>

<p>The R7000, on the other hand, just requires one or two clicks to install the update and automatically restart.</p>

<h3>And So Much More</h3>

<p>I usually install DD-WRT on any router I buy, but the R7000 has all the features I typically use, so I&rsquo;m just running the stock firmware.
Here are a few of the things I use most frequently:</p>

<ul>
<li>View attached devices</li>
<li>Port forwarding</li>
<li>Assign static LAN IPs</li>
<li>View traffic statistics</li>
</ul>


<h2>In Conclusion</h2>

<p>If you&rsquo;re tired of buying cheap routers that crap out after a year or two, I highly recommend the <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00F0DD0I6?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=213733&amp;creative=393185&amp;creativeASIN=B00F0DD0I6&amp;linkCode=shr&amp;tag=itsananderson-20&amp;linkId=BOLZOX4JTJAYBWR2">Nighthawk R7000</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
