<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Vim | Will Anderson]]></title>
  <link href="http://willi.am/blog/categories/vim/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://willi.am/"/>
  <updated>2017-10-05T17:58:23-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://willi.am/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Will Anderson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Editing Vim Macros]]></title>
    <link href="http://willi.am/blog/2014/06/21/editing-vim-macros/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-21T01:37:17-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://willi.am/blog/2014/06/21/editing-vim-macros</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Vim macros are great.
If you&rsquo;re not familiar with them, there&rsquo;s a great <a href="http://vim.wikia.com/wiki/Macros">Vim tips article</a>.</p>

<p>Something cool I&rsquo;ve discovered is that you can edit macros.
This is helpful if you accidentally mess up a macro recording, or decide you need to tweak it in some way.</p>

<p>If you recorded a macro to register <code>a</code>, you can paste its contents into the current document with <code>"ap</code>.
From there, you can edit the macro and then yank it back into the <code>a</code> register with <code>"ay</code></p>

<p>This also makes it easy to paste your macros into your vimrc for future use.</p>

<p><code>vim
" delete first word of line
let @d='0dw'
</code></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Understanding Vim Command Line and Search History]]></title>
    <link href="http://willi.am/blog/2014/04/08/understanding-vim-command-line-and-search-history/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-08T01:48:12-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://willi.am/blog/2014/04/08/understanding-vim-command-line-and-search-history</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you&rsquo;re a Vim user like me, you&rsquo;ve likely found yourself staring at a view like this and wondered:</p>

<h4>&ldquo;How&rsquo;d I get here, and how do I get away&rdquo;</h4>

<p><img src="//itsananderson.blob.core.windows.net/post-images/vim-command-line-history.png"></p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t dispair. You&rsquo;ve discovered Vim&rsquo;s command line history. This is the list of commands you&rsquo;ve run. They&rsquo;re stored in <code>~/.viminfo</code> or <code>~/_viminfo</code>, depending on your system configuration</p>

<p>There are actually two modes you can get into:
Command Line History, and Search History.
We&rsquo;ll cover both</p>

<p>If you didn&rsquo;t want to get into your command/search history, you can easily get back to normal mode by hitting <code>CTRL+C</code> twice</p>

<h2>Command Line History</h2>

<p>Command line history is activated by typing <code>q:</code>. I usually find myself in this mode after trying to type <code>:q</code> too quickly</p>

<p>This is actually a pretty useful tool.
You&rsquo;re basically opening a file that contains your command history, so you can treat it like you would a file you have opened in Vim.</p>

<p>Start by navigating through the commands.</p>

<ul>
<li>You can use <code>j</code> and <code>k</code> to move down and up.</li>
<li>You can search through the commands with <code>/&lt;searchtext&gt;</code></li>
</ul>


<p>Once you find the command you want to run, simply hit <code>ENTER</code> from &ldquo;Normal&rdquo; mode to run that command on the current file</p>

<h2>Search History</h2>

<p>Search history is activated by typing <code>q/</code>.</p>

<p>This is also a useful tool, though not as useful as command line history, in my opinion</p>

<p>Just like command line history, you can navigate through the history just like a regular file, and hit <code>ENTER</code> with the cursor over the desired search to perform that search on the current document</p>

<h2>Now You&rsquo;re Better at Vim</h2>

<p>When I figured out what these views meant, it took a scary &ldquo;how do I get out of this mode&rdquo; moment, and turned it into a &ldquo;this is useful&rdquo; moment.
Hopefully after reading this post, you&rsquo;ll feel the same way!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
